<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A thunder-clap to Sion-Colledge. Or, a catalogicall hint of the pulpit inveteracy, and apostacy, of that mischievous assembly, or mystery of iniquity, at Sion Colledge. By S.T: a cordiall friend to truth and peace, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>S. T.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95603</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T58</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E542_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205963</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865177</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865177</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117414</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95603)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117414)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 84:E542[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A thunder-clap to Sion-Colledge. Or, a catalogicall hint of the pulpit inveteracy, and apostacy, of that mischievous assembly, or mystery of iniquity, at Sion Colledge. By S.T: a cordiall friend to truth and peace, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>S. T.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 9 [i.e 7], [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for G.W. near the Royall-Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648 [i.e. 1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 12th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sion College --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117414:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117414:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A THUNDER-CLAP TO Sion-Colledge.</p>
            <p>OR, A Catalogicall hint of the Pulpit Inveteracy, and Apoſtacy, of that miſchievous Aſſembly, or myſtery of Iniquity, at <hi>Sion</hi> Colledge.</p>
            <p>By <hi>S. T.</hi> A cordiall Friend to <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hoſ. 9.8.</hi>
               </bibl> The Prophets are fooles, the ſpirituall man is mad.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 23.15.</hi>
               </bibl> Behold, I will feede the Prophets with wormwood, and make them drink the water of Gall, for from the Prophets of Jeruſalem, is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe gone forth into all the Land. <hi>Verſ. 26.</hi> They are Prophets of the deceit of their own heart.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 3.13.</hi>
               </bibl> Their throat is an open Sepulcher, with their tongues they have uſed deceit: the poyſon of Aſpes is under their lips.</q>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed for</hi> G. W. <hi>near the</hi> Royall-Exchange. 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117414:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117414:2"/>
            <head>A THUNDERCLAP TO <hi>SION COLLEDGE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHat? is <hi>Presbytery</hi> become a faction, will nothing ſatisfie them but a factious uſurpt intereſt of will and power: Boundleſly, and unſatiably to tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize over the Conſciences of conſcientious men: will they never leave bawling, unleſſe all intereſts bow down, and be made ſubordinate to their intereſt: now we ſee, and all rationall men may ſee (that are not reſolvedly blind) what kind of <hi>Presbytery</hi> that is, which hath been ſo vigorouſly contended for this many years, <hi>viz.</hi> meerely a domineering Intereſt over their Brethren, and to be Lords over Gods heritage: now their undermining ſubtilty is unmasked, and that myſtery of iniquity is diſcovered: and Antichriſt in the forme and ſhape of <hi>Presbytery</hi> muſt not think to deceive the Nations any more, and although Antichriſt hath more beguiling tricks then one: <hi>yet that man of ſin muſt be revealed, whom God will deſtroy with the ſpirit of his mouth.</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7.8. he can turn <hi>Prelate,</hi> and <hi>Presbyter,</hi> and <hi>Roya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt;</hi> conforme to any ſhape, and every forme wherein he can moſt cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly and plauſibly deceive the Nations: But who would have thought that they would have turned abſolute impoſters, profeſſed <hi>Royaliſts,</hi> and imbraced and ſhooke hands with ſuch horrible and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable Apoſtacy: (O baſe principles) can you at pleaſure, renounce and perfideouſly deſert that ancient juſt cauſe wherein you ſeemed to engage in, with all the godly party in the Kingdom 7. years agone, and ever ſince: can you without difficulty teare, rack, and wrend ſuch publique principles of juſtice, freedom, and common ſafety, (and as, if this were not enough:) But you muſt moſt irrationally lay aſide and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117414:3"/>forget all the limits and bounds of moderation: you muſt make it your only buſineſſe (contrary to the Goſpel) both in Preſſes and Pulpits, inveterately to rayle and envy againſt a ſuccesfull, faithfull Army: meerely and alone for proceeding in, and purſuance of thoſe very principles of juſtice, freedom, and common ſafety, in which you formerly engaged, though now apoſtatized: though in your letter to the Lord Gen. and generall Councel, you with brazen faces profeſſe you adhere to the ancient juſt cauſe, and you are the ſame men ſtill, and own the ſame principles you ever owned, (I wonder you are not aſhamed of this diſſembling:) give me leave to make uſe of your own phraſe: (be not you deceived, for God is not mocked;) and though you turn with the times, and change your principles for the advantage of the corrupt intereſts: yet God laughs you to ſcorn, (looke to it,) God from Heaven will ſo tranſact and regulate different mutable things, as that your inveteracy, and apoſtacy, ſhall manifeſtly appear to all the world: whereby unvindicable Infamy will unavoydably reſt upon you to poſterity.</p>
            <p>Do but ſee a little your corrupt partiall dealing; you perfideouſly connive and wink at that in your ſelves: which is the alone marke you ſhoote at in the Army, and others who are the objects of your invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teracy.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You rayle againſt them for uſurping that which is not proper to them, and upon this account, all the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Pulpits in the City muſt ring of them, as a ſeditious, factious Generation, and all the week long is little enough to ſtudy and knock your heads together: to bawle and mouth at them, with all the calumnies that can be inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the next Lords day: But I pray beare with me a little.</p>
            <p>Adhere a little to this aſſertion: you call them uſurpers, but I pray pull the beame out of your own eye, for it makes you judge partially and blindly: I think it would not be abſurdity, or rudeneſſe, to call you the moſt ambitious uſurpers in all the world; for ſuppoſe them to be uſurpers, as you call them; yet they uſurpe nothing but what is proper to men (though we deny this to your face:) But you muſt uſurpe and appropriate no leſſe then the alone proper prerogative of Chriſt, (<hi>viz.</hi>) to be law givers to the Church, and to be Lords over Gods heritage: as if Chriſt were not as faithfull in all his houſe as <hi>Moſes: Heb.</hi> 3.5. But through forgetfulneſſe muſt leave his inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo lame and imperfect as muſt needes ſtand in need of ſome addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117414:3"/>or detraction from men: what may demonſtrate you to be a faction, and what may illuſtrate your unparelleld uſurpation, if this may not, nay, if this doth not.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You ſay they delight to rule, and will make all things ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to them and their Intereſt: (ſurely you do but forget yourſelves) you ſuppoſe that to be in them, which is alone in yourſelves: you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide to ſet the ſaddle upon the right horſe, I muſt tell you, its a principle which they abhor; but a principle which you own &amp; contend for, &amp; it hath been your pulpit work for this many years together, to make all perſons, and Intereſts, ſtoope and couch to your Intereſt, and yet you call that preaching of the Goſpel, when preſumptuouſly you preach onely in purſuance of your own Intereſts, and how long have you deſired and wayted for that day, and for that power, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you might be whipping men into a ſubjection and ſubordination to your corrupt principles, Directories, and Doctrines; though never ſo oppoſite to the tenour and ſubſtance of the word of truth, and to the primitive inſtitutions of Chriſt; for the truth of this, let your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant actions witneſſe, and rationall men judge.</p>
            <p n="3">3. You go further, and cry out they act confuſedly and irregular; but if you conſider this well, you may very well hold your tongues: we need no other weapons to beat you then your own, is it not your own corrupt method, are you not alwayes ſplitting yourſelves upon this rock of irregularity and confuſion: will you believe it when you fee it? You call yourſelves miniſters of Chriſt, and of the Goſpel: (which I profeſſe, all things conſidered, is very queſtionable.) But if you are ſo, why do you not preach the Goſpel which is your own proper and alone work, and aquieſſe within the compaſſe of your own ſpheare and ſtation, and not in the ſame breath quite exceed your bounds, and turn Stateſmen: Nay, and which is worſe, to take the fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>womens trade out of their hands: (give me leave) are theſe the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of Miniſters of the new Teſtament: to envie, rayle, and ſcold, as if you had ſerved 7. years Apprentiſhip at <hi>Billings-gate;</hi> is this to preach the Goſpel, to divulge your own corrupt fancies, and your own humane inventions, and make hodge podge of the Goſpel: you are in your Element, when you are jumbling and confounding multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of diſtinct things of a retrogade nature into one bundle, and that Sermon is not accounted a Sermon amongſt you: wherein you do not moſt inviterately beſpatter, and throw dirt in the faces of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117414:4"/>them that are honeſter then yourſelves: either you muſt be bawling againſt Sectaries, or mouthing at the Army, or envying againſt the Parliament in its preſent form and conſtitution, and yet this you do ambitiouſly and falſly call preaching of the Goſpel: (what blind do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are theſe:) do not you hereby make the Doctrine of the Goſpel a Doctrine of diviſion, a Doctrine of ſedition and faction, a Doctrine of confuſion: and how do you rack and wreſt the infallible Scripture to the confuſed factious interpretations and expoſitions, and falſly you can render politicall expoſitions of ſpirituall Scriptures: if you muſt needes turn Stateſmen, one would ſuppoſe it moſt proper for you, when you are out of your Pulpits: and not ſo irregularly make your Pulpits Chayres of State, and ſo confuſedly jumble naturall, civill, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticall, military and ſpirituall things together: this hath been too to much your Antichriſtian method, and if impudence did not hinder, you might be aſhamed and bluſh at the thoughts of ſuch prevarica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: if this be regular, what is irregular, if this be order, what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, forbear leaſt it prove your confuſion.</p>
            <p>Another object of your Inveteracy, are a Company of godly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious men, whom you brand erronious and Hereticks: who do by that which you call Hereſie, in the ſincerity &amp; integrity of their hearts, worſhip the God of their Fathers, <hi>Act.</hi> 24.14. But the People are ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bituated to your perverſe Doctrines, which you doe ſo frequently ſow amongſt them; that all is taken for currant error &amp; hereſie; and on the contrary, for undoubted infallible truth that you ſet your ſtampe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be it never ſo ſcandalous and falſe. But if we come maturely and rationally, to examine what that is you call Error, and what that is you call Hereſie, and what that is you call Schiſme. Its all, and onely, ſuch perſons, and doctrines, that croſſe your uſurpt factious Intereſt of will and power; that refuſe ſubordination to your Government and Scepter; and from this rotten Principle radically flowes, all that inveterate railing, ſcandalous abominating, moſt intollerable backbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and miſchievous beſpattering of men, whom their Conſciences cannot but be (yea and are) convinc't, they are conſcientious godly men.</p>
            <p>But becauſe they obſtruct and ſtop the current and ſtreame of their premiſed factious Intereſt, meerely upon this very accompt, almoſt all the Pulpits in City and Kingdome muſt ring of them: O they are a ſeditious people, not worthy to live; they are the alone trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117414:4"/>of our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and never expect Peace while theſe Sectaries have a being amongſt us; (and juſt like the <hi>Phariſees) If we let this man</hi> (or theſe men) <hi>alone, all the world will beleeve on them,</hi> Joh. 11.48. And our trade that hath formerly bin the beſt trade in the Kingdom (<hi>viz.</hi> Preaching) that is like to be engroſſed from us; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, our honour, and eſteeme, and eminency in the world, that decreaſes alſo; and our power, and intereſt, that will be troden under foot; and therefore our beſt way is to doe, as the Pope alwaies doth; Vote godly men to be devilliſh, and then ſet the dogges on them; and the wild Beares and Tygers of the earth muſt be anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and encouraged to teare them in peeces; and if we can get but a Pattent to Monopolize this trade, and to Monopolize the Goſpel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our owne hands, then we ſhall be well enough; Is not this your method.</p>
            <p>For this is that which perplexes theſe men, to ſee other men, whom they ambitiouſly call Mechanicks and Lay-men; to ſell, or preach the Gopel at an under rate; becauſe they doe not preach for hire, as they doe; and preach for Honour and a reward as they doe; this makes them ready to gnaw their tongues for paine, and yet they think they cannot tumble out their venomes faſt enough; but raile on them, almoſt till they foame at the mouth; and in the midſt of this, are like a Fiſh in the water, in their deſired element; they are ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and habituated to this frame and forme, of Pulpit cavelling, and Pulpit inveighing, that I am Confident, were it poſſible, they could preach whiles dooms day, they would never forget this perverſe trade; and the reaſon is, becauſe they have ſo little reaſon, that they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forſt to make it up with paſſion: but what Goſpel is this, to patch up Sermons out of ſuch a deteſtable luſt, as paſſion is, and fill the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples eares with ſuch rayling ruffiſh.</p>
            <p>But if you were taught of God, and if you learnt the truth as it is in Jeſus, you would comfortably and freely acquieſce in the declaration of this truth; for this is the Goſpel method, and if you are Miniſters thereof, this is your alone worke, (<hi>viz.</hi>) to preach the truth: and conſequently, error and deluſion will fall to the ground. Never thinke to ſcatter and deſtroy error, by your irregular and perverſe jumbling, and inveighing againſt it: in ſo doing what doe you leſſe then delude the people; and like the Prieſts of olde, you cauſe the people to erre, <hi>Micha</hi> 3.5. For I hope you are not ſo ambitious to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117414:5"/>think that you are the only infallible Judges of truth: but you may, (you do) erre as well as others; and therefore, whilſt you perſiſt in this confuſion, you are ſo farre from convincing men of error, that you confirme them therein. Man is a rationall creature, and error where it is, it lies in the underſtanding; and therefore its onely rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, concurring with the power of truth, can enlighten the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and convince the perſon ſo erring. Error is no otherwiſe but a miſtake in the judgement, and the judgement muſt be ſatisfied and convinc't, before error can be ſubdued, this is undeniable; the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience that will adhere to what the judgment beleeves. Muſt you go whip the conſcience, now this is according to the rule of your invention: Not according to the infallible rule of Scripture. The Lord make the people of this Kingdome wiſer then their Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</p>
            <p>But now a few words touching your Apoſtacy: Beare with my Pen a little, for its no abſurdity to call it ſo. You are turn'd profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Royalliſts, and you are interwoven into the Kings principles; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that now the Kings deſigne is your deſigne, and your Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit worke is to propagate the Kings Intereſt, though retrograde and deſtructive to the publicke intereſt: &amp; you could own that perfidious treacherous treaty, &amp; adhere to Malignants in their engagements, &amp; pray devoutly for the reſtoring the King to his Crown, Scepter, and Dignity. (What is Presbytery Kingified now:) can you with the face of reaſon, or Chriſtianity, attempt or preſume to appear for the Kings intereſt. But truly, all things conſidered, we need not wonder at it: for Eccleſiaſticall Intereſt and Monarchicall Intereſt, hath been, and muſt be jumbled together, as interwoven one in another: Sute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to that Text, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.7. <hi>The beaſt muſt beare the whore.</hi> A lively portracture of your Church. Such is your Intereſt, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand unleſſe upheld by the Kings of the earth; your Kingdome is of this world; Contrary to the nature of the Kingdome of Chriſt; and upon this account, you may well ſtruggle and buſſle for Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie; becauſe your Intereſt depends upon it. But one would think, you ſhould not be ſo mad, and ſo perfidiouſly irrarionall, as to attempt, owne, or proſecute the deſtructive propagation of the corrupt Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Intereſt of this King; ſo palpably deſtructive to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and to the whole publick Intereſt.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you looke back a little, and take a particular ſurvay of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117414:5"/>wonderfull tranſacting of things, in relation to the Kings proceedings: did ever any Engage, Contrivers, contend for him, and proſper: hath God, thinke you, (I appeale to your Conſciences) fought ſo wonderfully, ſo unparalleldly, ſo miraculouſly, againſt both foraigne, and domeſtick ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and blaſted all Plots, Contrivances, Attempts, and Stratagems, for nothing, I ſay, is it for nothing, that God hath done all this.</p>
            <p>Nay, what hath the People of <hi>England</hi> fought for this many yeares, if not for a free, and impartiall execution of Juſtice upon Capitall offenders, and originall Authors of all the blood, miſery, and ruine of the People of this Nation: and dare you (I ſay, dare you) in perſon preſſe, or Pulpit attempt to ſtop the Current of Juſtice, (I wonder at your Impudence) is not Impartiall Juſtice, the alone ſollid Foundation of all the peace, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and freedome that can be expected?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But you would have the King exempted becauſe there is no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident for the like Action, (I wonder at your weakneſſe.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is your great Argument that makes a monſter through Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and Kingdome. But, If examined, as light as vanity it ſelfe; (for mind) if no Preſident can be produced, or extracted from our Anceſtors. Then this Parliament hath made, and may proceed, to make a preſident for Poſterity, upon ſuch ſollid, ſtable, anſwerable, juſtifiable grounds of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Equity, Juſtice, and Common ſafety: that all the world, if they judge impartially, cannot poſſibly contradict: now as Preſidence are not conſtant Rules to act by; ſo no former preſident whatſoever can bound or limit the proceedings and actions of the ſucceeding Generations: becauſe preſidents of neceſſity, may, and muſt differ, according to the mutable different con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of times. But the reaſon of no preſident is cleare, becauſe no King did ever Perſonally, or Commiſſionally, ſo perfidiouſly attempt the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine and deſolation of the publike Intereſt; and therefore no cauſe of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of this nature. I hope gainſayers will be ſilent in this; for whoever deny it, muſt exceed the bounds of Reaſon, and common ſence.</p>
            <p>And whereas you falſly affirme and declare in your pernitious letter-to the Lord Gen. that its an action contrary to the Law of God and man: if you ſtudy and prevaricate while doomes day, you can never prove it: I demand, whether the Law of God, or Nations: the Law of equity, juſtice, and ſafety: do more or leſſe in reference to dignity, or a title of Honour: exempt a man from deſerving juſtice, <hi>he that ſheds mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed. Gen.</hi> 9.6. now this text nor no other text hath the leaſt limitation or reſtriction to the title King. But if he be a man, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret as falſly as you will, or can; he is not exempted, but comes within the compaſſe of juſtice.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:117414:6"/>
            <p>But when every thing deſert you, then as your laſt ſupport, you fly to the Covenant, and you can pull and wrack that with all the falſe miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions that can be invented, to patch up all your weakneſſe and invete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, and like your perfideous <hi>Scots,</hi> your dear Brethren, you can ſtrike through the heart and bowells of the Covenant, with the Covenant in your mouthes.</p>
            <p>But if it be demanded, why I direct my ſpeech to <hi>Sion</hi> Colledge: its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I conceive that to be the conſervatory, or fountain originall from whence flowes all that rubbiſh, traſh, and trumpery that is publiquely di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulged in moſt Pulpits throughout the City, in your monthly morning Lectures, and every Lords day: though I deſpiſe not your Lectures, if either intended or acted for good.</p>
            <p>Is this the beſt eggs you can hatch at your dayly and weekly meetings at <hi>SionColledge;</hi> that as the reſults of your pernicious Counſels, you muſt allot and appoint every one his work: one ſhall raile againſt the Army, another inveigh againſt the preſent forme and Conſtitution of the Parliament; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other muſt pray and preach devoutly for reſtoring the King; another cry up the ſecluded Members. What ruffiſh is here to ſtuffe Sermons withall? have you nothing elſe to doe, but to poyſon, pervert, diſtract, and diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et the Spirits of men, who would otherwiſe willingly, and freely aquieſe, were they not by you inraged, incouraged, incenſed, and animated againſt the Army and Parliament.</p>
            <p>If you were not as blind as Beetles, you may be ſatisfied; that the Army in conſcience could doe no leſſe; unleſſe they were ſo mad as to ſtand ſtill and ſerve 7. or 8. years labour, travell, and hazard, ſo perfidiouſly loſt: and reſigne up their Liberties and Freedoms (which is the price of their blood) into the hands of theirs, and the Kingdomes thrice Conquer'd e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; Its as cleare as the Sun, that the Parliament was then going about to ſell them, with all the honeſt party in the Kingdom, into the blood and revenge of an enraged and tyrannicall King; who I am confident, would under ſome pretence or other, have cut the throats of all the godly in the Kingdome by thouſands; and all the Liberty, Freedom, Priviledge, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Intereſt, fought for eight yeares together, would have been ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up into perjury and profeſſed tyranny; and all the circumſtances, and parts of that treacherous agreement for Peace with the King, conſidered; compact, and patcht up together, were deſtructive to the publick intereſt; and upon this account, whether the neceſſity were not abſolute, or elſe ruine unavoidable: I leave to the judgements of rationall, impartiall prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipled men publike. If the Army which you contemn, had not tooke more for the care then you, but derogated from their principles, as you have don,
<pb facs="tcp:117414:6"/>all the godly in the Kingdome might have hang'd their harps upon the Willow trees, and ſought a reſidence in a ſtrange Land (and get you like ungratfull wretches) now they have done the Kingdom ſuch unparallel'd ſervice, you could now cut their throats for their labour.</p>
            <p>I wonder, you are not aſhamed to bring ſuch an infamy upon your Coat; are you not in a direct way, to lay a plat-forme for a new Summers bloody ruining War, do you love to fiſh in troubled waters, and delight to be kindling the fire of diſcention and diſcord, and perpetuall rigid oppoſition in the Kingdome: (looke to it) theſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples are rotten principles; and unleſſe you forbeare, they will make you obnoxious to the juſt Cenſures of all men: and if a third war follow, we muſt be neceſſitated to conclude from rationall grounds, that you are the fomenters and abettors thereof; and that it is the conſequent of your inveterate rayling, and perverſe mouthing againſt your Bretheren, who would willingly (if poſſible they can crave ſo mvch favour at your hands) as Free-born Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> injoy a peaceable and quiet reſidence amongſt you. Its well ſuch curſt Cowes as you are, have ſhort hornes; otherwiſe, if ſpeciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence did not interpoſe, you would teare and rack your diſcenting Brethren, as you have torne and rackt your own principles.</p>
            <p>But what means your unceſſant inveighing&amp; clattering againſt the Parl. Some of you call them a broken Parl. others no Parl. and that Apoſtate <hi>Prinne</hi> calls them an unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary <hi>Iunto.</hi> And the great reaſon is, becauſe (they ſay) they are under a Force, and conſequently, no legall Authority (Good lack, what a baſe pvinciple and Intereſt will doe.) Its high time that the Clergy ſhould be made Judges of Parliamentary Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: have they not voted themſelves the ſupream Authority of the Kingdome, and conſequently, a free Repreſentative; and it was your own Argument not long ſince, that themſelves were the competent ſole Judges of their own Authority; and have they not joyntly approved of the reaſons of the Gen. Counſell, for ſecluding, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing ſome of their treacherous Members, for perfidious diſerting, and betraying their truſt. But becauſe you cannot have a Negative voice, and becauſe they proceed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and againſt your approbation, advice, and concurrence: therfore you will diſpute the legality of their authority: what perfidious (in and out, faſt &amp; looſe) dealing is this?</p>
            <p>For notwithſtanding, that unparallel'd cruel violence of the riotous tumultuous Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices, upon the Houſe, in <hi>July,</hi> 1647. forcibly keeping the Speaker in his Chaire, and putting things to the queſtion themſelves, after the Houſe was deſolved, and when after this, the Speaker, with many other faithfull Members of the Houſe were neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated to flye to the Army: In whoſe abſence the Royall Party choſe a new Speaker, and attempted (might and maine) to leavy a force againſt the Army, thereby engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Kingdome in blood. Notwithſtanding all this, your reſolved blindneſſe could not own it as a force: but then they were the Parl. of <hi>England,</hi> and you could freely read, (and enforce obedience to) their deſtructive Ordinances for raiſing of Forces: and ſtill ſo long as they have been your Parl. and ſerved your Inrereſt, ſo long, and no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb facs="tcp:117414:7"/>have they bin the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi> You can dance no longer, then they pipe your Intereſt.</p>
            <p>And you can like <hi>Royaliſts</hi> profeſſe and declare in your Pulpits, againſt the Legal juſt proceedings of Parl. (I profeſſe its inſufferable) you deteſt the thoughts of calling the King to an account, and its unparallel'd and deſtructive for Proteſtant Kingdomes, to ſtaine themſelves with the bloud of their Kings. Nay, which is more then all; Its contrary to the ſubtill Nationall Covenant. Mr. <hi>Calamie,</hi> that old Conformiſt, will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver leave turning and conforming for the beſt advantage of his Intereſt; but muſt divulge ſuch nonſenſicall doctrines as theſe, to confound the eares of his Auditory.</p>
            <p>But in order, Its deſtructive and unparallel'd, to be ſtain'd with the bloud of Kings; but minde, its neither the one nor the other for you to be ſtain'd with your owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, factious, uſurpt tyrannicall Intereſt: although you engage the whole Kingdom in warre and bloud to accompliſh it. But what a guilt and ſtaine it is for a Proteſtant Kingdome to execute Iuſtice: Is it not a trecherous and deſtructive principle, to deteſt the thoughts of Juſtice. I wiſh you appeare not to be (for you give us probable grounds to beleeve it,) the chiefe obſtructers of Juſtice this 7. years together, by your Parliament whiſpering and inſinuating, having had ſuch an Antichriſtian influence upon the Houſe.</p>
            <p>But then you fly to the Covenant, to catch ſome falſe interpretation, the better to enforce the Kings intereſt, and your delight in prevaricating, &amp; cheating the people: in taxing the Army with your own perjury for all bonds in the Covenant, (if you are not mad or blind) touching preſerving the King, are only conditionall (not abſolute:) But you are poſſitively and abſolutely engaged to bring all Delinquents to condigne pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and would it not be partiality and perjury in the higheſt degree, that that grand Delinquent and originall publique Author and Abettor of all our blood-ſhed, ruine, and miſery, ſhould be exempted, and inferiours only puniſhed, who acted com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionally from him, and actually for him; I am confident, you may as well remove a Mountain into the midſt of the Sea, as deny it to be juſtice in the impartiality of it; and how hath God contmually croſt, confounded, battered, and ſhattered to peeces all plots, contrivances, and attempts to vindicate the truth of the premiſes: not to be trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherized, and creacified into ſlavery (which you promoted:) but to produce a free cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of impartiall Juſtice. The premiſes maturely and ſolidly conſidered: your Pulpit barking and mouthing againſt Parl. Army, and your Brethren: is nothing but a probable introduction, to a third bloudy War; to the great hazard (or at leaſt much dammage) to the publique intereſt, and as much as poſſible you over ſhaddow and eclipſe thoſe dawnings and appearings of liberty, freedom, priviledge, and ſolid ſecurity to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique intereſt, that upon foundations of Juſtice and righteouſneſſe are (we hope) flowing in as the proper fruites of all ſo long fightings, waytings, and expectations.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
